[Music]
in 2015 researchers in california found
bovine leukemia var stitched into the
dna of human breast cancer tumors from
mastectomies
at such higher rates than was found in
normal breast tissue taken from breast
reduction surgery that they calculated
that as many as 37 percent of breast
cancer cases may be attributable to
bovine leukemia virus exposure likely
through the consumption of milk or meat
obtained from infected animals in
response the milk and meat industry seem
more concerned about consumer confidence
than consumer cancer
but scientifically the research priority
turned to could the california results
be replicated
the answer it turns out
was yes they were replicated among women
in iran replicated in brazil
in australia the link was even stronger
in texas the same thing
women diagnosed with breast cancer were
found to be so much more likely to have
bovine leukemia virus dna in their
breast tissue compared with women
without cancer that the attributable
risk was calculated at 51.82 percent
indicating that this mean dairy virus
could be responsible for at least one
half of the breast cancer cases among
the women in texas they studied
all in all
six of the eight studies performed to
date found the virus in human breast
tissues which suggest strongly that blv
does infect humans and breasts can be
targets of infection
and four of the five studies that were
able to compare infection rates in
cancerous tissue versus normal breast
tissue
found that the odds of finding the virus
in the tumors was an average of four
times higher
how does that compare to other breast
cancer risk factors if you go on hormone
replacement for five years you can bump
up your breast cancer risk by 30 percent
if you take the pill for more than a
dozen years your risk may go up 40
if you're obese when you're older your
risk can go up 60 having a first degree
relative with breast cancer may double
your risk but having your breasts
infected with bovine leukemia virus may
quadruple your risk increase your risk
hundreds of percent
the only risk factor is more potent than
blv infection we're having
broccoli gene mutations like angelina
jolie has or a high dose of ionizing
radiation like being in the wrong place
at decidedly the wrong time
beyond confirmation one study suggested
that older patients had a greater
likelihood of testing positive for
bovine leukemia virus that makes sense
and if blv is from exposure to dairy and
meat the older we get the more meals
we've had the more opportunities become
infected over time researchers also
discovered that the virus comes first
present in some breast tissues three to
ten years before cancer was diagnosed
this argues against the idea of viral
invasion of already malignant cells
quashing the theory that maybe the virus
is somehow just attracted to the cancer
after the fact
could this explain the consistent
findings that breast cancer tissue is
more likely to harbor infection again
the data showed no the virus appeared to
come first
now this review doesn't provide absolute
proof that blv is a cause of breast
cancer but based on the best available
balance of evidence blv infection does
indeed appear to be a breast cancer risk
factor
the latest revelation is this now been
found in human blood too
this has a number of potential
ramifications blood banks for example
don't screen for it so it's possible you
can get it from consuming meat or dairy
or getting blood from someone who
consumed meat or dairy
this could also mean that blv could
cause leukemia in people too
a dozen chimpanzees two infant chimps
were fed milk from cows naturally
infected with blv and they both died of
leukemia
we didn't even know chimps could get
leukemia this certainly suggests the
possibility of transmission or induction
of leukemia through the ingestion of
milk from blv infected cows or
blood-borne spread could carry the virus
to other organs in cattle the virus
causes blood cancers but this may just
be because dairy cattle are turned into
hamburger when they're still so young so
maybe they don't have time for tumors to
grow in other organs
how concerned should we be about bovine
leukemia virus
it's not clear yet whether this is a
good news story or a bad news story i
mean if subsequent studies show that blv
does cause breast cancer in humans this
will have significant repercussions for
the dairy and cattle industries but that
means there's something we can do about
it
perhaps attempt should be made to
eradicate the infection from cattle now
rather than wait for the final word 21
nations have eradicated blv from their
dairy cattle in contrast in the u.s the
blv prevalence just keeps going up
if the industries are not going to step
up and try to eliminate the disease then
the least they could do is eliminate
some of the practices that spread the
disease between animals
blv is spread via blood through
contaminated needles
saw or gouge dehorners tattoo pliers ear
taggers hoof knives nose tones and other
tools of the agribusiness trade
though in view of the emerging
information about blv and human breast
cancer it may be prudent to encourage
the complete elimination of blv and
cattle particularly in the dairy
industry the hope is that either way it
may help reduce the scourge
of breast cancer
[Music]
so